<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mariage of Prince Fredericke, and the Kings daughter, the Lady Elizabeth, vpon Shrouesunday last VVith the shovves on land and water, before, and after the wedding, as also the maskes and reuells in his Highnes court, with the running at the ring, by the Kings Maiestie, the Palsegraue, Prince Charles, and diuers others of the nobilitie.</title>
            <title>Marriage of the two great princes, Fredericke Count Palatine, &amp;c: and the Lady Elizabeth, daughter to the Imperial Majesties of King James and Queene Anne.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105595</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841322</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841322</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5897</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01243)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5897)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1660:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mariage of Prince Fredericke, and the Kings daughter, the Lady Elizabeth, vpon Shrouesunday last VVith the shovves on land and water, before, and after the wedding, as also the maskes and reuells in his Highnes court, with the running at the ring, by the Kings Maiestie, the Palsegraue, Prince Charles, and diuers others of the nobilitie.</title>
                  <title>Marriage of the two great princes, Fredericke Count Palatine, &amp;c: and the Lady Elizabeth, daughter to the Imperial Majesties of King James and Queene Anne.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Now the second time imprinted, with many new additions, of the same tryumphs, performed by the gentlemen of the Innes of Court in the Kings pallace of white Hall.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] C[reede] for W. Barley, and are to be sold by W. Wright, at his shop neere S. Pulchers Church, at the signe of the Harrow,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An enlarged edition of: The marriage of the two great princes, Fredericke Count Palatine, &amp;c: and the Lady Elizabeth, daughter to the Imperial Majesties of King James and Queene Anne.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>The first word of the title is xylographic.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Ioyfull triumphs at the royall mariage.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth, --  Queen, consort of Frederick I, King of Bohemia, 1596-1662.</term>
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5897:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5897:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> MARIAGE OF Prince FREDERICKE, and the Kings daughter, the Lady ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH, vpon Shroueſunday laſt.</p>
            <p>With the showes on land and water, before, and after the wedding, as alſo the Maskes and Reuells in his Highnes Court, with the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>at the Ring, by the Kings Maieſtie, the</hi> Palſegraue, <hi>Prince</hi> Charles, <hi>and diuers others of the Nobilitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>NOW THE SECOND TIME IMPRINTED, with many new additions, of the ſame tryumphs, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>by the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court in the Kings Pallace of white Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>At London Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>W. Barley,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>W. Wright,</hi> at his ſhop neere S. Pulchers Church, at the ſigne of the Harrow, 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5897:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5897:2"/>
            <head>THE MARIAGE OF Prince Fredericke, and the Kings Daughter, the Lady ELIZABETH, vpon Shroue-ſunday laſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing deſirous to giue ſatiſfaction to certaine of my acquaintance in the countrey, moſt willing to vnderſtand the manner of the tryumphes holden at the royall marriage, of his Maieſties daughter, Princeſſe <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue made meanes for the true intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences thereof, and I hope according to the content of the Reader, I haue ſet forth here a true diſcourſe of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the ſhewes and Fireworkes vpon the waters before the mariage performed, vpon thurſday night, being the eleuenth of Februarie.</p>
            <p>Then the imitation of a Sea Fight vpon Saterday fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>Alſo of the royall and Princely paſſage of Prince <hi>Palſegraue</hi> with his renowned bride, to his highnes chappell at white Hall, where in the preſence of his Maieſtie and the noble ſtate, they were married, to make vs reioyce, with a wiſhed happines, with the maſkes and reuels following, ſhewes of more royaltie, then euer in this Age was ſéene in the court of England.</p>
            <p>Therefore let the Readerd hereof, prepare himſelfe, to entertaine them with extraordinarie ioy, and receiue the good will of the writer, for a tribute, to be paide as a dew to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:5897:3"/>
               <head>The manner of the fireworkes ſhewed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Thames vpon the Thurſday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wedding.</head>
               <p>TO begin theſe tryumphant ſports, his highnes, the Quéenes Maieſtie, Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> with the Princes <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his royall bride, and the reſt of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of England, vpon Thurſday the eleuenth of Februarie in the euening, being placed in the galleries and windowes about his Highnes Court of white Hall, where in the ſight of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of people, many artificiall concluſions in Fireworkes were vpon the <hi>Thames</hi> performed, and that the pleaſurable ſights on the water, might equall the ſumptuous ſhowes on the land, thus they procéeded.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for a welcome to the beholders, a peale of ordinance like vnto a terrible thunder ratled in the ayer, and ſéemed as it were to ſhake the earth: Immediately vpon this, a Racket of Fire burſt from the water, and mounted ſo high into the Element that it dazeled the beholders eyes to looke after it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, followed a number more of the ſame faſhion, ſpred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo ſtrangely with ſparkling blazes, that the ſkie ſéemed to be filled with fire, or that there had béene a combate of darting ſtarres fighting in the ayre, and all the time theſe continued, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cannons planted in the fields adioyning made thundring muſicke, to the great pleaſure of the beholders.</p>
               <p>After this in a moſt curious manner, an artificiall fireworke with great wonder was ſéene flying in the ayre, like vnto a dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, againſt which an other fierie viſion appeared flaming like to Saint <hi>George</hi> on Horſebacke, brought in by aburning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanter, betwéene which was then fought a moſt ſtrange battell continuing a quarter of an hower or more: the dragon being vanquiſhed, ſéemed to rore like thunder, and withall burſt in péeces and ſo vaniſhed, but the champion with his flaming horſe for a litle time made a ſhew of a truimphant conqueſt, and ſo ceaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5897:3"/>After this, was heard an other ratling ſound of Cannons, almoſt couering the ayre with fire and ſmoake, and forthwith appeared out of a hill of earth made vpon the water, a very ſtrange fire flaming vpright like vnto a blazing ſtarre: After which flew forth a number of rackets ſo high in the ayre, that we could not chuſe but approue by all reaſons that Arte hath excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Nature, ſo artificially were they performed, and ſtill as the Chambers and Culuerines plaide vpon the earth, the fireworkes danced in the ayre, to the great delight of his Highnes, and the other Princes.</p>
               <p>Out of the ſame mount or hill of earth flew an other ſtrange péece of artificiall fire-worke, which was in the likenes of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Hart, running vpon the waters ſo ſwiftly, as it had bene chaced by many huntſmen.</p>
               <p>After the ſame, iſſued out of the mount, a number of hunting hounds made of fire burning, purſuing the aforeſaid Harte vp and downe the waters, making many rebounds and turnes with much ſtrangenes: ſkipping in the ayre, as it had bene a vſuall hunting vpon land.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the noble delights of Princes, and prompt were the wits of men to contriue ſuch Princely pleaſures.</p>
               <p>Where Kings commands be, Art is ſtretcht to the true depth, as the performance of theſe Enginers haue here approued.</p>
               <p>But now again to our wiſhed ſports, when this fiery hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting extinguiſhed, and that the Elements a little cleared from fire and ſmoake, there came ſayling vp, as it were vpon the Seas, certaine ſhippes and gallies brauely rigd with top and top gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, with their flagges and ſtreamers wauing like men of warre, which repreſented a Chriſtian Nauie oppoſed againſt the Turkes, where after they had a while houered, preparing as it were to make an incurſion into the Turkiſh countrey, they were diſcouered by two Towers or Caſtles of defence, ſtrongly furniſhed to intercept all ſuch inuading purpoſes, ſo ſending forth the reports of a cannon, they were brauely anſwered with the like from the gallies, banding fire and powder one from an other, as if the God of battels had béene there preſent.</p>
               <p>Here was the manner of a Sea Fight rightly performed:
<pb facs="tcp:5897:4"/>
Firſt by aſſayling one an other, all ſtriuing for victorie, and purſuing each other with Fire and ſword, the Caluerines merily plaid betwixt them, and made the ayre reſound with thundring Ecchoes, and at laſt, to repreſent the ioyes of a victorie, the Caſtles were ſacked, burned and ruinated, and the defenders of the ſame forced to eſcape with great danger.</p>
               <p>During the time of all theſe triumphant exerciſes, there was not a man vnbuſied, but euery one laboured, ſome on Land, ſome on Water, ſome one way, ſome an other, to moue his Highnes, and the reſt of his princely friends a pleaſing content, which hee and the other Princes with a gratious acceptance, applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to the great comort of the performers, and no litle ioy to the beholders.</p>
               <p>The next morning, being Fryday, his Highnes, not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to grace the following ſports with his preſence, gaue cauſe of forbeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with ſome reſt to the Enginers for their great toyle the night before.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, it was thought conuenient that a whole dayes preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be made, in prouiding againſt the Saterdayes paſtimes, which moued a more longing deſire in the harts of his ſubiects to ſée the ſame, which at the time appointed was in this maner accomplied.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The manner of a Sea fight, ſhewed vpon the Thames, vpon the Saterday before the wedding.</head>
               <p>BEtwéene the howers of two and thrée of the clocke the ſame day in the after noone being Sroue-ſaterday, the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, accompanied with the Quéene, and the reſt of the Princes and Péeres of eſtate, to adde the more glory to theſe pretended ſhowes, placed themſelues in great royaltie vpon the priuie ſtaires of white Hall, where after a while expecting the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the deſired fireworkes, the Lord Admirall ſent forth two or thrée gentlemen in a whirrie, with a flagge or banner to ſignifie the King, and the Nobilities tarriance for the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb facs="tcp:5897:4"/>
which was anſwered with an Intelligence by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, from a great cannon, whereupon a certaine Veneſian man of Warre, and a ſhip called a Caruell, came proudly with their flagges and colours ſayling vp, in the ſight of ſeuentéene Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh gallies which lay houering vpon Lambeth ſide, betwixt whom was a moſt royall and praiſe worthy Imitation of a ſea fight in ſuch ſort performed, as if the danger of ſuch an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe had bene by true action attempted, all which explaines the honors of martialiſts, and made his Maieſtie, with many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of people of all ſorts, and of many Nations eye-witneſſes of the true manner of ſuch like incounters. But not to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome in my diſcourſes, I will briefly explaine the incounters as they paſſed.</p>
               <p>There was a barre or a kind of artificiall fence made vpon the riuer of Thames with Barges and Lighters chained together, to kéepe out paſſengers, which otherwiſe with much vnrulines would haue hindered the paſtimes, and much troubled the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, but being thus hemde in, as it were vpon the maine Seas, the two Venetian ſhippes as I ſaid before, falling within danger of the Turkiſh gallies, indured a freſh encounter, and long time moſt worthily defended themſelues, but by reaſon of the number of the gallies, they were at laſt boarded, taken, and carried as boote and prize vnder the commaund of a Turkiſh Caſtle, which repreſented and bare the name of the caſtle of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geir,</hi> Furniſhed with 22. well approued great péeces of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which was contriued and built vpon <hi>Lambeth</hi> ſide, at a place named <hi>Stand-gate,</hi> inuironed with craggie Rocks as the ſaid Caſtle is now ſcituate in Turkie.</p>
               <p>After the Gallies had taken theſe Venetian ſhips, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them into the Turkiſh Admiralls commaund, they had ſight of an other Argoſay or Galliaza, which ſéemed to be of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which likewiſe after a fierce conflict they made prize of, and with much tryumph rendred the ſame vp alſo to the Turkiſh Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
               <p>After this, vpon a ſuddaine there was a thundring peale of Ordinance or Chambers placed in <hi>Lambeth Marſhe,</hi> wherevpon the Scoutes and Watches of the Caſtle, diſcouered an Engliſh
<pb facs="tcp:5897:5"/>
Nauie, to the number of fiftéene Saile of the Kings Pinnaces, making vp towards the point, with their red croſt Streamers moſt gallantly wauing in the Ayre, to the great delight of all the beholders, which as then ſeemed to couer ouer the Thames in Boates and Barges.</p>
               <p>Neare vnto this place ſtood a high built watch Tower, or Beacon of the Turkes, which at the firſt ſight of the Engliſh Nauie was ſet on fire, as the manner is at all ſuch incurſions, which blazing Light (as it ſéemed) gaue notice to the Caſtle, and cauſed a readines in the ſame for defence: In the meane time, the Kings Pinnaces and the Turkiſh Gallies ioynde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt whom, were ſhowne many ſtrange attempts, euen as they had ventured their very liues for their countries ſafeties: they ſpared neither powder nor pollicie, to ſacke one an other, but on both ſides beſtird themſelues ſo brauely, that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe withall the reſt of his attendants were therewith much delighted: At laſt the Gallies being ouercharged with long and forward incounters of the Engliſh Nauie, for refuge and ſhelter made new vnto the Caſtle, which began likewiſe to play brauely vpon the Engliſh, and with their thundering ordinance made as it were the ground to ſhake.</p>
               <p>The Kings Nauie to anſwere them was not backward in a performance, but made the ayre gloomie with fire and ſmoake rorering from their lowde mouthed Cannons.</p>
               <p>The fight for a time continued fiercely, the victorie leaning to neither ſide, either of them attempting to aſſault and board each other, but at laſt the Gallies being ſore bruzed and beaten, began to yéeld, wherevpon the Engliſh Admirall fell downe and caſt anker before the Caſtle, and then ſpared not in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to thunder off their Ordinance, whereat the Turkes yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded both Caſtle and Gallies, and ſubmitted to the conqueſt of the Engliſh Admirall, who fiered many of the ſaid Gallies, ſacked the Caſtle, and tooke priſoner the Turkiſh Admirall, with diuers Baſhawes and other great Turkes, and alſo recouered the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Shippes, before taken by the Gallies. After the performance of all theſe aforeſaid, the Engliſh Admirall, in a moſt tryumphant manner carried as a priſoner, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall
<pb facs="tcp:5897:5"/>
of the Gallies attired in a red Iacket with blew ſléeues, according to the Turkiſh faſhion, with the Baſhawes, and the other Turkes, guarded to his Highnes priuie ſtaires of white Hall, where his grace, Prince <hi>Palſegraue,</hi> and his Lady remained, which priſoners were lead by Sir <hi>Robert Manſfield,</hi> to the Lord Admiral, and by him they were conueyed to the Kings Maieſtie, as a repreſentation of pleaſure, which to his Highnes moued delight, and highly pleaſed all there preſent.</p>
               <p>All theſe aforeſaid paſtimes were moſt nobly performed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the howres of thrée and ſixe in the after noone, to the great content as well of forraigne nations as of our owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try people, whereof in one place, and at one time, hath bene ſeldome ſéene a greater number.</p>
               <p>Alſo for a Farewell to this dayes pleaſures, a traine of Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers were diſcharged in Saint <hi>Georges</hi> Field of a long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and of ſuch an Ecchoing thunder, that they euen ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the hearers. Thus ended Saterdayes ſhewes vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, being the eue of this great Mariage-day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The manner of the Marriage vpon Shroue-ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, with the Royall paſſage of Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> and <hi>his Bride to his Maieſties Chappell at White-Hall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt now to relate and make knowne the royall paſſage of the renowmed Bride-groome and his faire Bride, (for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of many thouſands) as they entred into his Highnes Chappell at White-Hall: the next day being Sunday, euen ouercomes me with a reioycing deſcription.</p>
               <p>The Court being placed full of people of many Eſtates, ſortes, and Nations, and their eyes and hearts fixed to behold the pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious glory of this Marriage in great Royaltie.</p>
               <p>Firſt came the <hi>Palſ-graue,</hi> from the newe built Banquetting-houſe, attired in a white Satten ſute, richly beſet with Pearle and Golde, attended on by a number of young gallant Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, both Engliſh, Scottiſh, and Dutch, all in rich manner, euery one ſtriuing to excéede in ſumptuous habilliaments, fitte
<pb facs="tcp:5897:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for the attendants of ſo princely a Bride-groome. After came the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in her Virgin-robes, clothed in a gowne of white Satten richly embrodered, lead betwéene her royall bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Northampton:</hi> vpon her head a crowne of refined golde, made Imperiall (by the Pearles and Dyamonds thereupon placed,) which were ſo thicke beſet, that they ſtood like ſhining pinnacles, vpon her amber coloured haire, dependantly hanging plaighted downe ouer her ſhoulders to her Waſte, betwéene euery plaight a role or liſte of Gold-ſpangles, Pearles, Riche ſtones, and Diamonds, and withall, many Diamonds of ineſtimable value, imbrothered vpon her ſléeue, which euen dazeled and amazed the eies of the beholders: her traine in moſt ſumptuous manner, carryed vp by fourtéene or fiftéene Ladies, attired in white Satten gownes, adorned with many rich Iewells.</p>
               <p>After went a traine of Noble-mens Daughters, in white Veſtements, gloriouſly ſet foorth: which Virgin Bride-maides attended vpon the Princeſſe, like a ſkye of Celeſtiall ſtarres, vpon faire <hi>Phoebe.</hi> After them, came another traine of gallant young Courtiers, flouriſhing in ſeuerall Sutes, Embrothered and Pearled, who were Knightes, and the ſonnes of great Courtiers: After them, came foure Herolds at Armes, in their rich coates of Heroldrie, and then followed many Earles, Lords, and Barrons, as well of Scotland as England, in moſt noble manner, then the king of Herolds, bearing vpon his ſhoulder a Mace of golde, and then followed the honourable Lords of his Highnes priuie Councell, which paſſed along after the Traine towards the Chappell, and then came foure reuerend Biſhops of the Land in their Church abilliaments: After them foure Sargiants of the Mace in great ſtate, bearing vpon their ſhoulders foure rich Enamelled Maces.</p>
               <p>Then followed the right Honorable the Earle of <hi>Arundell,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the Kings Sword: And then in great Royaltie the Kings Maieſtie himſelfe in a moſt ſumptuous blacke ſute, with a Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amond in his hatte of a wonderfull great value; Cloſe vnto him came the Quéene, attired in white Satten, beautified with much embrothery, and many Diamonds: Vpon her attended a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:5897:6"/>
of marryed Ladies, the Counteſſes, and wiues of Earles and Barrons, apparelled in moſt noble manner, which added glory vnto this triumphant time and Marriage.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the paſſages of our States of England, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying the princely Bride and Bridegroome to his Highnes Chappell, where after the celebration of the Marriage, contracted in the preſence of the King, the Quéene, Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the reſt aforeſaide: they returned into the banquetting houſe with great ioy.</p>
               <p>The Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being thus made a Wife, was led backe, not by two Batchellors as before, but by the Duke of <hi>Lineux,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> in a moſt reuerend manner, before the <hi>Palſegraue.</hi> At his returne from the chappell, went ſixe of his owne Country gallants, clad in crimſon Veluet, laide excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly thicke with gold lace, bearing in their hands sixe ſiluer Trumpets, who no ſooner comming into the Banquetting houſe, but they preſented him with a melodious ſound of the ſame, flouriſhing ſo delightfully, that it greatly reioyced the whole Court, and cauſed thouſands to ſay at that inſtant time, <hi>God giue them ioy, God giue them ioy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus preparing for dinner, they paſſed away a certaine time, and after fell to Dancing, Maſking, and Reuelling, according to the cuſtome of ſuch Aſſemblies, which continued all the day, and part of the night in great pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The order of the Mundayes ſhowes, with the Kings running at the Ring with the Nobilitie of the Land.</head>
               <p>THe next day (being Shroue-munday) by the King and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of England was ſpent in great honour, where their rich Robes of Eſtate ſeconded the day before, with many commendable graces: for the whole Court ſo gloriouſly ſhined with Imbrothered abilliaments, that it made euen a ſmiling chéerefulnes ſit vpon the countenance of many thouſand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5897:7"/>For the Kings Maieſtie in his owne perſon, accompanied with his braue ſpirited ſonne Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of great <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> the Royall Bride-groome, <hi>Count Pallatine,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Linneux,</hi> with diuers other of the Earles and Barrons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> together with the praiſe-worthy Péeres of the Netherland Prouinces, performed many famous races at the Ring, an exerciſe of much renowne and honour, and the knightly ſports, and the Royall delights onely befitting the dignitie of Kings and Princes, and of the chiefeſt Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>Firſt, about the rayles or liſts in the Tylf-yard, adioyning to White Hall, were placed many Herolds at Armes, to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the honourable atchiefements of theſe knightly Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, and withall, the Knight marſhall of England, and his ſeruants, all in new liueries with their ſtaues of office, to abate the too forward vnrulines of many diſordered people, which otherwiſe would haue much troubled the Turnaments, and as an ayde vnto them, many of his Highnes Yoemen of the Guard were attendant in the liſtes, and withall, moſt of the Kings Trumpetters in their rich imbrothered coates, the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners and Knights of his graces houſhold with their guilded Pole-axes, guarding as it were in a round, the King with his Knightly followers.</p>
               <p>The Quéenes Maieſtie, with her daughter the Princes <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> attended on by many of the greateſt Ladies of the Land, being placed in the Galleries and windowes of the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting houſe, In the preſence of many thouſands of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, the King mounted vpon a Stéed of much ſwiftnes, was the firſt that began the honourable paſtimes, and like a moſt noble martialiſt tooke the Ring vpon his ſpeare, thrée ſeuerall times together, whereat the trumpets ſtill ſounded to the great ioy of all the beholders.</p>
               <p>After him the Illuſtrious Prince, <hi>Count Palatine,</hi> vpon a horſe of that braue courage, which ſéemed to ſtand vpon no ground, where with a ſpirit of much forwardnes, he tooke the Ring vpon his ſpeare twiſe together, ſo lightly, and ſo nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that the whole aſſembly gaue him high commendations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5897:7"/>After him, the braue young flower, and hope of England, Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> mounted as it were vpon a Spaniſh Iennet, that takes his ſwiftnes from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of the winde, moſt coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, and with much agillitie of hand, tooke the Ring clearely foure times in fiue courſes, which was in the eye of the Kings Maieſtie and the Nobilitie, there preſent, a ſight of much admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and an exceeding comfort to all the land.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Lineux,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Arundell,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> the Lord <hi>Haddindon,</hi> with diuers other Barrons of England, and Scotland, afterward, in honour of this magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent mariage, performed many worthy races, and many times tooke the Ring with much ſtrangenes, a pleaſure ſo princely, that it euen made the beholders hearts to leape with ioy.</p>
               <p>The Quéenes Maieſtie, with her daughter the Princes, all the while ſtanding in the windowes, as eye-witneſſes to theſe noble delights, ſmiled with much chéerefulnes, graciouſly than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them all for their loues, but eſpecially the new married Bride, in honour of whoſe mariage all theſe courtly paſtimes were performed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Maskes and Reuells preſented by the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court, vpon the Munday night.</head>
               <p>THe procéeding Night, ſports were as ſumptuous, as the paſſed dayes, and in as gallant a manner performed: whereof to ſatiſfie the deſirefull Reader, I muſt thus ſpeake of.</p>
               <p>The Gentlemen of the Innes of Court, in the beſt and rareſt manner they could deuiſe, prepared Maſkes and Reuells in the Court, that night to be preſented: and about the houres of eight or nine, they paſſed from the <hi>Roles</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane,</hi> to <hi>White Hall,</hi> in as royall manner as euer gallants did to the Court of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, there rode ſome thrée ſcore braue ſpirited Gentlemen vpon great Bard-horſes, moſt richly trapped with imbrothered
<pb facs="tcp:5897:8"/>
furnitures, themſelues attired in cloth of golde and tiſſue, moſt gloriouſly ſhining, lighted by a number of torches, to beautifie the ſhowe with more Eye-pleaſing delights.</p>
               <p>After them, ſome ſixe and thirtie Maſkers, diuided by twelues, in moſt ſtrange Anticke ſutes, in a moſt admirable and ſtately manner. Likewiſe vpon coſtly trapped ſtéedes, each of them hauing a Blackamoore Page attending on Horſe backe, with torch lights burning in their hands.</p>
               <p>After them followed thrée Charriots of Maſkers and Reuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, in garments of a meruellous faſhion, ſo artificially diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that they moued much wonder. Vpon them attended a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Footemen, bearing burning torches, and withall, many trumpets ſounding melodiouſly, which was a ſight both to Eye and Eare, of an excéeding glorie: Theſe performed many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull dances in his Highnes preſence, and other paſtimes of pleaſure, to the great comfort of all the beholders, and to the high honours of this magnificent Marriage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Tryumphs and Reuells vpon the next night following, being Shroue-tueſday.</head>
               <p>THe next day being Shroue-tueſday, a day of pleaſure, and Iollitie by cuſtome, but farre more delightfull by reaſon of this magnificent mariage, which moued many occaſions of mirth in his Highnes court, for euery day in ſeuerall attires, were the Nobilitie of the land ſeene flouriſhing in the chamber of preſence, and much was the coſt ſpent in banqueting of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne eſtates, as wel Princes Embaſſadors, as the Péeres and Nobles attending vpon the <hi>Palſegraue,</hi> which vpon this day was as royally performed, as vpon the former.</p>
               <p>The bountie of his Maieſtie excéeded, for his Highnes court was frée for all people of faſhion, as well Cittizens as others, and few came thither that departed without kind entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for liberalitie, with ſpredding armes kept open houſhold, whereby the time may well be recorded for a time of Princes pleaſures, by reaſon Princes were the maintainers thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5897:8"/>The night procéeding, much expectation was made of a ſtage play to be acted in the great Hall by the Kings Players, where many hundreds of people ſtood attending the ſame: but it hapned contrarie, for greater pleaſures were preparing, which in this manner were performed, as vpon the night before a moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous maſke came to court, by the Gentlemen and ſtudients of the lawe, from the Roles Office, by land, ſo ſome thrée hundred Gentlemen more, of the ſame eſtate and calling, by water, to equall them in ſtatelines, came likewiſe vp the Thames by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with a maſke to White Hall, at whoſe ſetting forth from Wincheſter-houſe in their Barges, a peale of ordinance placed on the backeſide, ſéemed as it were thunder, the Barges were beautified with many flagges and Streamers, lighted with a number burning creſſets and torches, attended on by Drums and Trumpets, which ſounded all the way moſt melodiouſly, the Gentlemen and maſkers, had moſt glorious and rich ſuites of cloth of gold and ſiluer, with other Robes of much delight and pleaſure, their entertainements in Court were gratious, and their performance as curious as the ſkill and Art of wit could deuiſe, at which the King and all the royall aſſembly there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, tooke high contentment.</p>
               <p>The Kings Maieſtie, in the royaltie of his minde, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of theſe rare deuiſes of the Gentlemen of the Innes of Court, (being moſt of them ſonnes to great ſtates of the land) inuited them all within few daies after, to a royall banquet, where not onely by his Highnes, but by the <hi>Palſegraue</hi> and his Bride, they had moſt kind and friendly thankes.</p>
               <p>And now to conclude my diſcourſe, the ioyes hereof were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in manie places, as well Citie as Court: for the Belles of <hi>London</hi> rung generally in euery Church, and in euery ſtréete Bon-fires blazed abundantly, there was neither coſt nor paines ſpared by his Highnes ſubiects, that any way might giue ſignes of ioy, for the Marriage of his princely daughter to her royall Huſband, whom God bleſſe with long hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, and Throanes of Angelles kéepe and defend. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
